Now that you've had the intro to, let's see how we can use him and where we'll actually use them.
So let's start off by creating a list.
Say we want to store a list of all the friends you want to invite to a party.
So we could do like what we did before and say maybe friend one as a variable and let's go and call
that friend Mary and then go friend two so you can see this can start to get a little bit repetitive,
especially if you've got a lot of friends.
Friend three.
Friend four.
And you're going to keep having to add them all into your list like that.
And that's going to get like just a bit messy to have to deal with all of those different variables.
Essentially, they all belong to one list.
They're your party friends.
Okay.
So let's uh, instead of going on and on about and typing in 520 different variables, let's just store
them in one place.
So to create a list, let's call this list friends.
All you have to do is put these two square brackets.
So now I actually have a list.
It's an empty list.
It isn't storing anything, but Python now sees this as a list.
Okay, so it's actually a special type of data.
So this is now you've actually created you see it's distinct from just being an integer or a string.
This is actually a list type that you can now work with.
So let's start storing those frames in our list.
Now remember these are names.
So we're going to store them all as strings.
And to store a string we use inverted commas.
Now to separate the different names we use commas.
So first name Mary next friend okay let's go again with Fred.
And let's put my name in here.
We can be friends okay.
You can go on as long as you want.
Let's go.
One more name to okay.
So here's a list of four friends.
Again, if we print this, it isn't going to show anything.
But what Python has done is it's taken this list and Mary, Fred, Sarah, Charlie and stored all of
that inside this variable called friends.
So now let's first just print it just to make sure that is what it's doing.
Print the variable friends.
And there you see it's stored it as a list.
It's not a string.
It hasn't stored them all as one sentence inside.
So you can actually see each of inverted commas.
Each of them has a little set of inverted commas around them, indicating that each of them is an individual
string.
So it sees that as four separate names.
Okay.
So now we have these in a list.
But now let's just say I'm wanting to send an invitation to Sara.
How can I now say I want to send it to Sara.
So what we're going to do is in all programming languages we have something called indexing.
What that basically means is each element in our list has a specific number associated with it.
So now you would think that if I had to ask you what number in the list is Sara, you're going to go,
well that's easy.
Sara is Mary Fred Sara Sara is three.
But you would be wrong.
Wrong.
Computers are just a little bit different.
Like we said earlier, computers might seem a bit confusing to people who don't know anything about
them, but as soon as you start learning the way they work their language, it really makes so much
more sense.
And it really it's it's very simple.
So what you need to remember with computers counting starts from zero.
So here instead of going one, two, three, four, five whatever we go 0123.
So where you might have thought before Sarah would be number three in the list, it is actually indexed
two.
So let's just say now I want to be able to print out that name.
Sarah I don't want any of the other names.
I just want Sarah in order to pull out that name.
We use what I said earlier, indexing.
And again, this might seem a bit confusing, but we're using square brackets again, so maybe easy
way to remember it is if I want to call a number from the list.
I'm using the same square brackets, but it doesn't necessarily mean the same thing at all.
This means that you want to call that number again.
So what I've typed here, I've typed the name of a list friends, and I'm saying I want index two from
that list.
Index position number two.
So 012.
And down the bottom here you see we found Sarah.
So if we tried zero if we wanted Mary we would actually use zero.
There we go.
At the bottom.
It's pulled out Mary.
Okay.
So what happens if we put, uh five.
Good question.
That's a good question.
There we go.
Not happy.
You'll see it on the bottom there.
It's giving you an index error list index out of range obviously because there isn't a position five
or a value in position five in your list.
And obviously the same with negatives, but actually complained about that fact because there are only
four different elements in this list and it only goes up to index three.
Okay.
So again, instead of now having to type hello comma friend one hello comma friend two, we can just
easily change that number.
And let's just say you're invited.
And we wanted to invite Charlie.
And don't forget that comma.
Okay.
And then you could do it with the others.
And we actually going to later on look at something called loops, which makes this even more powerful.
Okay.
So as you can see, slowly things are starting to get more and more complicated.
And as your programs start to get longer and longer and eventually you're going to have programs that
can be thousands of lines long.
We want to try and keep track of what we're doing, and by the time you're down on line 373, you might
scroll up, back on back to line four and have no idea what you were typing there.
So in order to help us as programmers and also help other people when they might read your code or try
and understand what you've been doing, we have something called comments.
So all our comment is, is it's very simple.
It's a hashtag and whatever you want.
Okay.
Now this hello hashtag hello.
What Python basically does is it completely ignores this.
So comments are for yourself.
It's to help you.
Pathan.
When it runs the program, it doesn't even see this.
So anything after that hash tag, it completely ignores.
You can have a space and say whatever.
So the point of commenting is very important.
As Sarah said, a lot of programmers think, oh, they're just going to rush through and code.
But understand this even if someone else is not having to look at your code, if you're going to look
at someone else's code and they haven't commented it, you have no idea what they've done.
But even you yourself, you come back a week or a month later and you look at your code and you cannot
remember why you did certain things.
So it is very important.
It's a good habit to get into.
To start to add comments, you can add comments on a line, you can add comments on its own line.
So you might want to say you know the code below.
Here is where we are.
We are printing out the friends names, etc. really important to put as many comments as you can just
to remind yourself and others who are reading the code what is going on.
So it's a good habit to get used to it.
You will be very thankful if you put comments in, because you're guaranteed you're going to come back
later and you're going to go, what in the world was I doing there?